<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sam>
	<group name="Content">
		<item value="Purpose is evident">
			<explanation>
				It is important that readers/clients readily understand the
				intended purpose of the instruction for them. If they don't clearly perceive the
				purpose, they may not pay attention or may miss the main point.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Purpose is explicitly stated in title, or cover illustration, or introduction.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Purpose is not explicit. It is implied, or multiple purposes are stated.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				No purpose is stated in the title, cover illustration, or introduction.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Content about behaviors">
			<explanation>
				Since adult patients usually want to solve their immediate health
				problem rather than learn a series of medical facts (that may only imply a solution),
				the content of greatest interest and use to clients is likely to be behavior
				information to help solve their problem.			
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Thrust of the material is application of knowledge/skills aimed at
				desirable reader behavior rather than non-behavior facts.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				At least 40 percent of content topics focus on desirable behaviors or actions.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Nearly all topics are focused on non behavior facts.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Scope is limited">
			<explanation>
				Scope is limited to purpose or objective(s). Scope is also limited
				to what the patient can reasonably learn in the time allowed.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Scope is limited to essential information directly related to the
     			purpose. Experience shows it can be learned in time allowed.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Scope is expanded beyond the purpose; no more than 40 percent
				is non-essential information. Key points can be learned in time allowed.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Scope is far out of proportion to the purpose and time allowed.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

	<group name="Literacy Demand">
		<item value="Reading grade level" hasAnalysis="true">
			<explanation>
				Unless the instruction presents the topics completely without text
				(via visual, demonstrations, and/or audio), the text reading level may be a
				critical factor in patient comprehension. Reading formulas can provide a reasonably
				accurate measure of reading difficulty.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				5th-grade level or lower (5 years of schooling level).
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				6th-, 7th-, or 8th-grade level (6-8 years of schooling level).
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				9th-grade level and above (9 years or more of schooling level).
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Writing style, active voice">
			<explanation>
				Conversational style and active voice lead to easy-to-understand
				text. Example: "Take your medicine every day." Passive voice is less effective.
				Example: "Patients should be advised to take their medicine every day." Embedded
				information, the long or multiple phrases included in a sentence, slows
				down the reading process and generally makes comprehension more difficult.		
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					Both factors: 
					<list-item>Mostly conversational style and active voice.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Simple sentences are used extensively; few sentences contain
						embedded information.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				<list>
					<list-item>About 50 percent of the text uses conversational style and active voice.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Less than half the sentences have embedded information.</list-item>
				</list>
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				<list>
					<list-item>Passive voice throughout.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Over half the sentences have extensive embedded information.</list-item>
				</list>
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Vocabulary uses common words">
			<explanation>
				Common, explicit words are used (for example, doctor vs. physician).
				The instruction uses few or no words that express general terms such
				as categories (for example, legumes vs. beans), concepts (for example, normal
				range vs. 15 to 70), and value judgments (for example, excessive pain vs. pain
				lasts more than 5 minutes). Imagery words are used because these are words
				people can "see" (for example, whole wheat bread vs. dietary fiber; a runny
				nose vs. excess mucus).
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					All three factors: 
					<list-item>Common words are used nearly all of the time.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Technical, concept, category, value judgment (CCVJ) 
							words are explained by examples.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Imagery words are used as appropriate for content.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				<list>
					<list-item>Common words are frequently used.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Technical and CCVJ words are sometimes explained by examples.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Some jargon or math symbols are included.</list-item>
				</list>
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				<list>
					Two or more factors: 
					<list-item>Uncommon words are frequently used in lieu of common words.</list-item> 
					<list-item>No examples are given for technical and CCVJ words.</list-item>
					<list-item>Extensive jargon.</list-item>
				</list>
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Context is given first">
			<explanation>
				We learn new facts/behaviors more quickly when told the context
				first. Good example: "To find out what's wrong with you (the context first), the
				doctor will take a sample of your blood for lab tests" (new information).
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Consistently provides context before presenting new information.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Provides context before new information about 50 percent of the time.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Context is provided last or no context is provided.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Learning aids via 'road signs'">
			<explanation>
				Headers or topic captions should be used to tell very briefly
				what's coming up next. These "road signs" make the text look less formidable,
				and also prepare the reader's thought process to expect the announced topic.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Nearly all topics are preceded by an advance organizer (a statement
				that tells what is coming next).
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				About 50 percent of the topics are preceded by advance organizers.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Few or no advance organizers are used.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

	<group name="Graphics">
		<item value="Cover graphics show purpose">
			<explanation>
				People do judge a booklet by its cover. The cover image often is the
				deciding factor in a patient's attitude toward, and interest in, the instruction.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					The cover graphic is 
					<list-item>friendly</list-item>
					<list-item>attracts attention</list-item>
					<list-item>clearly portrays the purpose of the material to the intended audience.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				The cover graphic has one or two of the superior criteria.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				The cover graphic has none of the superior criteria.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Type of graphics">
			<explanation>
				Simple line drawings can promote realism without including distracting
				details. (Photographs often include unwanted details.) Visuals are
				accepted and remembered better when they portray what is familiar and easily
				recognized. Viewers may not recognize the meaning of medical textbook
				drawings or abstract art/symbols.		
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					Both factors: 
					<list-item>Simple, adult-appropriate, line drawings/sketches are used.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Illustrations are likely to be familiar to the viewers.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				One of the superior factors is missing.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				None of the superior factors are present.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Relevance of illustrations">
			<explanation>
				Non-essential details such as room background, elaborate borders,
				unneeded color can distract the viewer. The viewer's eyes may be "captured"
				by these details. The illustrations should tell the key points visually.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Illustrations present key messages visually so the reader/viewer
				can grasp the key ideas from the illustrations alone. No distractions.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				<list>
					<list-item>Illustrations include some distractions.</list-item> 
					<list-item>Insufficient use of illustrations.</list-item>
				</list>
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				<list>
					One factor: 
					<list-item>Confusing or technical illustrations (non-behavior related).</list-item> 
					<list-item>No illustrations, or an overload of illustrations.</list-item>
				</list>
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Lists, tables, etc. explained">
			<explanation>
				Many readers do not understand the author's purpose for the
				lists, charts, and graphs. Explanations and directions are essentiaL
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Step-by-step directions, with an example, are provided that will
				build comprehension and self-efficacy.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				'How-to' directions are too brief for reader to understand and
				use the graphic without additional counseling.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Graphics are presented without explanation.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Captions used for graphics">
			<explanation>
				Captions can quickly tell the reader what the graphic is all about,
				where to focus within the graphic. A graphic without a caption is usually an
				inferior instruction and represents a missed learning opportunity.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Explanatory captions with all or nearly all illustrations and graphics.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Brief captions used for some illustrations and graphics.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Captions are not used.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

	<group name="Layout and Typography">
		<item value="Layout factors">
			<explanation>
				Layout has a substantial influence on the suitability of materials.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					At least five of the following eight factors are present:
					<list-item>Illustrations are on the same page adjacent to the related text.</list-item>
					<list-item>Layout and sequence of information are consistent, making it easy for the
				   		patient to predict the flow of information.</list-item>
					<list-item>Visual cuing devices (shading, boxes, arrows) are used to direct attention to
				   		specific points or key content.</list-item>
					<list-item>Adequate white space is used to reduce appearance of clutter.</list-item>
					<list-item>Use of color supports and is not distracting to the message. Viewers need not
				   		learn color codes to understand and use the message.</list-item>
					<list-item>Line length is 30-50 characters and spaces.</list-item>
					<list-item>There is high contrast between type and paper.</list-item>
					<list-item>Paper has non-gloss or low-gloss surface.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				At least three of the superior factors are present.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				<list>
					<list-item>Two (or less) of the superior factors are present.</list-item>
					<list-item>Looks uninviting or discouragingly hard to read.</list-item>
				</list>
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Typography">
			<explanation>
				Type size and fonts can make text easy or difficult for readers at
				all skill levels. For example, type in ALL CAPS slows everybody's reading
				comprehension. Also, when too many (six or more) type fonts and sizes are
				used on a page, the appearance becomes confusing and the focus uncertain.		
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					The following four factors are present:
					<list-item>Text type is in uppercase and lowercase serif (best) or sans-serif.</list-item>
					<list-item>Type size is at least 12 point.</list-item>
					<list-item>Typographic cues (bold, size, color) emphasize key points.</list-item>
					<list-item>No ALL CAPS for long headers or running text.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Two of the superior factors are present.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				One or none of the superior factors are present. Or, six or more
				type styles and sizes are used on a page.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Subheads ('chunking') used">
			<explanation>
				Few people can remembering more than seven independent
				items. For adults with low literacy skills the limit may be three- to five-item	
				lists. Longer lists need to be partitioned into smaller "chunks."
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				<list>
					<list-item>Lists are grouped under descriptive subheadings or "chunks."</list-item>
					<list-item>No more than five items are presented without a subheading.</list-item>
				</list>
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				No more than seven items are presented without a subheading.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				More than seven items are presented without a subheading.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

	<group name="Learning Stimulation, Motivation">
		<item value="Interaction used">
			<explanation>
				When the patient responds to the instruction-that is, does something
				to reply to a problem or question-chemical changes take place in the
				brain that enhance retention in long-term memory. Readers/viewers should
				be asked to solve problems, to make choices, to demonstrate, etc.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Problems or questions presented for reader responses.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Question-and-answer format used to discuss problems and solutions
				(passive interaction).
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				No interactive learning stimulation provided.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Behaviors are modeled and specific">
			<explanation>
				People often learn more readily by observation and by doing it
				themselves rather than by reading or being told. They also learn more readily
				when specific, familiar instances are used rather than the abstract or general.		
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Instruction models specific behaviors or skills. (For example, for
				nutrition instruction, emphasis is given to changes in eating patterns
				or shopping or food preparation/cooking tips; tips to read labels.)
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Information is a mix of technical and common language that the
				reader may not easily interpret in terms of daily living (for example:
				Technical: Starches-80 calories per serving; High Fiber-l-4
				grams of fiber in a serving).
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Information is presented in non-specific or category terms such as the food groups.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Motivation -- self-efficacy">
			<explanation>
				People are more motivated to learn when they believe the
				tasks/behaviors are doable by them.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Complex topics are subdivided into small parts so that readers
				may experience small successes in understanding or problem
				solving, leading to self-efficacy.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Some topics are subdivided to improve the readers' self-efficacy.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				No partitioning is provided to create opportunities for small successes.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

	<group name="Cultural Appropriatness">
		<item value="Match in logic, language, experience">
			<explanation>
				A valid measure of cultural appropriateness of an instruction is
				how well its logic, language, and experience (inherent in the instruction)
				match the LLE of the intended audience. For example, a nutrition instruction
				is a poor cultural match if it tells readers to eat asparagus and romaine lettuce
				if these vegetables are rarely eaten by people in that culture and are not sold
				in the readers' neighborhood markets.
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Central concepts/ideas of the material appear to be culturally
				similar to the LLE of the target culture.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Significant match in LLE for 50 percent of the central concepts.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Clearly a cultural mismatch in LLE.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
		<item value="Cultural images and examples">
			<explanation>
				To be accepted, an instruction must present cultural images and
				examples in realistic and positive ways.		
			</explanation>
			<superior>
				Images and examples present the culture in positive ways.
			</superior>
			<adequate>
				Neutral presentation of cultural images or foods.
			</adequate>
			<not-suitable>
				Negative image such as exaggerated or caricatured cultural characteristics, actions, or examples.
			</not-suitable>
		</item>
	</group>

</sam>